Hamilton Fish Collection
Hamilton Fish Collection
1843-1892
Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893.
1 linear ft.
Papers of the American statesman, legislator, New York State governor, 1848. Outgoing letters (104), and photocopies of letters of Hamilton Fish; outgoing and incoming photcopies of letters of Sarah Baker, Julia Kean Fish, and Stuyvesant Fish, and a single item of outgoing correspondence of Hamilton Fish (1849-1936). Also, 1 account book (1844-1851).
150122
Biographical History
Hamilton Fish (1808-1893) was an American statesman, politician and lawyer.
Fish was born in New York City to Nicholas Fish and Elizabeth Stuyvesant, graduated from Columbia in 1827, and was admitted to the bar in 1830. He was elected to the House of Representatives (Whig Party) and served there from 1843 and 1845, then as lieutenant governor (1847-1848) and governor (1849-1850) of New York.
In 1851 he was elected to the United States Senate where, among other things, he was a member of the U.S. Senate Committee on Foreign Relations and part of a moderately anti-slavery faction. During the Civil War Fish was a member of the Union Defence Committee which raised and equipped troops, and was appointed by President Lincoln to the board of commissioners for the relief and exchange of Union prisoners of war.
After the war President Ulysses S. Grant appointed Fish Secretary of State, a position he held from 1869 to 1877. In this capacity he negotiated a number of treaties between the United States and various foreign powers, and presided at the peace conference between Spain and the allied republics of Peru, Chile, Ecuador and Bolivia, which resulted in a general truce between those countries. He also advocated testing for consular candidates to determine if they were truly qualified for duty at a consulate.
In addition to his goverment service, Fish was President of the New York Historical Society (1867-1869), trustee of the Lenox Library and the Astor Library (which evolved into the New York Public Library), and served as a trustee of Columbia University for more than fifty years. His namesake son, grand-son, and great-grandson all served in the House of Representatives for the state of New York; other descendants include diplomat Nicholas Fish, New Jersey Senator Hamilton Keane, governor of New Jersey Thomas Kean, and railroad executive Stuyvesant Fish.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Hamilton Fish Collection includes correspondence, account books, and memorabilia. Correspondence spans more than forty years and includes outgoing and incoming. The latter contains photocopies only and most is from Fish's wife, Julia Kean Fish, and other family members. Financial material contains account books covering the years 1844-1851. Memorabilia contains miscellaneous items.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is divided into incoming and outgoing. Outgoing is further divided into originals and photocopies and then arranged chronologically, while incoming is arranged alphabetically by sender. Account books are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
See also
Stuyvesant Fish Letter
.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; Baker, Sarah.; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893.; Fish, Hamilton, II, 1849-1936.; Fish, Julia Kean.; Fish, Stuyvesant, 1851-1923.; Fish family.; Legislators -- United States.; Governors -- New York (State); Politicians -- United States.; Statesmen -- United States.; Account books.; Correspondence.; Governors.; Legislators.; Politicians.; Statesmen.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing (originals)
    - 1844 (Box 1)
    - 1847-1857, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - 1861-1863, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1865-1866, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1869-1879, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - 1881-1882, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1884-1889, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - 1889 (Box 2)
    - 1891-1892, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Outoing (photocopies)
    - 1843 (Box 1)
    - 1846-1847, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1849 (Box 1)
    - 1851-1852, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1865 (Box 1)
    - 1869-1874, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - 1876-1877, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1879 (Box 1)
    - 1881-1882, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Incoming (photocopies)
    - Baker, Sarah, 1866; 1868,; 1870,; undated; includes 1 folder of transcriptions; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Fish, Julia Kean, 1850; 1852-1854,; 1866,; 1869-1874,; 1876-1880,; 1884,; undated; 34 folders (Box 2)
    - Fish, Stuyvesant, 1877 (Box 2)
    - Unknown and miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Of others
    - Silas Wright to C. W. Lawrence, 1865; relates to the application of one N. W. Wales for a clerkship in the Customs House; no apparent connection to Fish (Box 2)
- Financial material
  - Account books, inserts, 1844-1851 (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)